upei.ca 2011-05-31

# Privacy Main Page | University of Prince Edward Island | University of Prince Edward Island

##  UPEI Personal Information and Privacy: Policy and Resources

On January 1, 2004, the third and final phase of the Federal Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (PIPEDA) legislation came into effect with respect to provincially regulated organizations not covered by "substantially similar" legislation. What underlies the Federal legislation is a list of ten principles of fair information practices (Schedule 1 of the Act), which form ground rules for the collection, use, and disclosure of personal information. These principles give individuals control over how their personal information is handled in the private sector. An organization is responsible for the protection of personal information and the fair handling of it at all times, throughout the organization and in dealings with third parties. Care in collecting, using, and disclosing personal information is essential to continued confidence and good will of members of the University and larger PEI communities. The basic principles underlying the legislation are: accountability; identifying the purposes for the collection of personal information; obtaining consent; limiting collection; limiting use; disclosure and retention; ensuring accuracy; providing adequate security; making information management policies readily available; providing individuals with access to information about themselves; giving individuals a right to challenge an organization's compliance with these principles.

In light of this, the University of Prince Edward Island recognizes that it has an obligation and a commitment to protecting the privacy of those who work and study here. The University shall make its students, staff, and faculty aware of the importance of maintaining the confidentiality of personal information and shall advise them of the existence of this policy and its application to the collection, use, and disclosure of personal information through both printed and electronic means. Regulations dealing with the collection, storage, utilization, and the dissemination of personal information concerning its members is part of the University's ongoing effort to ensure that decisions concerning individuals are based on accurate information; that information gathered for one purpose is not used inappropriately for another; and that the privacy of individuals is not invaded through disclosure of sensitive information to third parties without the necessary approvals.

If you have complaints, concerns or questions about the University's policies and response to privacy, please contact the UPEI Privacy Officer, Mark Leggott: Robertson Library, 550 University Dr. C1A 4P3 - 902-566-0460, mleggott@upei.ca.

  * Other 
    * [Fact Sheet on Municipalities, Universities, Schools and Hospitals](http://www.privcom.gc.ca/fs-fi/02_05_d_25_e.asp) (Privacy Commissioner of Canada)
